<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Florian Wilhelm - talk</title><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/feeds/talk.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://florianwilhelm.info/</id><updated>2019-12-20T18:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Are you sure about that?! Uncertainty Quantification in AI</title><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/2019/10/uncertainty_quantification_in_ai/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-10T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T18:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Florian Wilhelm</name></author><id>tag:florianwilhelm.info,2019-10-10:/2019/10/uncertainty_quantification_in_ai/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the advent of Deep Learning (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DL&lt;/span&gt;), the field of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; made a giant leap forward and it is nowadays applied in many industrial use-cases. Especially critical systems like autonomous driving, require that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DL&lt;/span&gt; methods not only produce a prediction but also state the certainty about the prediction in order …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the advent of Deep Learning (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DL&lt;/span&gt;), the field of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; made a giant leap forward and it is nowadays applied in many industrial use-cases. Especially critical systems like autonomous driving, require that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DL&lt;/span&gt; methods not only produce a prediction but also state the certainty about the prediction in order to assess risks and&amp;nbsp;failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my talk, I will give an introduction to different kinds of uncertainty, i.e. epistemic and aleatoric. To have a baseline for comparison, the classical method of Gaussian Processes for regression problems is presented. I then elaborate on different &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DL&lt;/span&gt; methods for uncertainty quantification like Quantile Regression, Monte-Carlo Dropout, and Deep Ensembles. The talk is concluded with a comparison of these techniques to Gaussian Processes and the current state of the&amp;nbsp;art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was presented at &lt;a href="https://de.pycon.org/"&gt;PyCon.&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; PyData Berlin 2019&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://bigdataconference.lt/2019/"&gt;Big Data Conference Vilnius 2019&lt;/a&gt;. The slides are available on &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/FlorianWilhelm2/uncertainty-quantification-in-ai"&gt;SlideShare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="800" height="500"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/LCDIqL-8bHs'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="machine-learning"></category><category term="uncertainty quantification"></category><category term="data science"></category></entry><entry><title>Querying NoSQL with Deep Learning to Answer Natural Language Questions</title><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/2019/01/querying_nosql_with_deep_learning_to_answer_natural_language_questions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-29T11:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-29T11:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Florian Wilhelm</name></author><id>tag:florianwilhelm.info,2019-01-29:/2019/01/querying_nosql_with_deep_learning_to_answer_natural_language_questions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Almost all of today’s knowledge is stored in databases and thus can only be accessed with the help of domain specific query languages, strongly limiting the number of people which can access the data. In our work, we demonstrate an end-to-end trainable question answering (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;QA&lt;/span&gt;) system that allows a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Almost all of today’s knowledge is stored in databases and thus can only be accessed with the help of domain specific query languages, strongly limiting the number of people which can access the data. In our work, we demonstrate an end-to-end trainable question answering (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;QA&lt;/span&gt;) system that allows a user to query an external NoSQL database by using natural language. A major challenge of such a system is the non-differentiability of database operations which we overcome by applying policy-based reinforcement learning. We evaluate our approach on Facebook’s bAbI Movie Dialog dataset and achieve a competitive score of 84.2% compared to several benchmark models. We conclude that our approach excels with regard to real-world scenarios where knowledge resides in external databases and intermediate labels are too costly to gather for non-end-to-end trainable &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;em&gt;Querying NoSQL with Deep Learning to Answer Natural Language Questions&lt;/em&gt; was presented at &lt;a href="https://aaai.org/Conferences/AAAI-19/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IAAI&lt;/span&gt;-19&lt;/a&gt; and can be downloaded on &lt;a href="https://aaai.org/Papers/AAAI/2019/IAAI-BlankS.88.pdf"&gt;aaai.org&lt;/a&gt;. There is also a simplified blog post about the same topic on the &lt;a href="https://www.inovex.de/blog/seqpolicynet-nlp-elasticsearch/"&gt;inovex blog&lt;/a&gt; by my colleague Sebastian&amp;nbsp;Blank.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data science"></category><category term="nlp"></category></entry><entry><title>Performance evaluation of GANs in a semi-supervised OCR use case</title><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/2018/10/performance_evalution_of_gans_in_a_semi-supervised_ocr_use_case/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-24T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-24T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Florian Wilhelm</name></author><id>tag:florianwilhelm.info,2018-10-24:/2018/10/performance_evalution_of_gans_in_a_semi-supervised_ocr_use_case/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Even in the age of big data labelled data is a scarce resource in many machine learning use cases. We evaluate generative adversarial networks (GANs) at the task of extracting information from vehicle registrations under a varying amount of labelled data and compare the performance with supervised learning techniques. Using unlabelled data shows a significant&amp;nbsp;improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Online vehicle marketplaces are embracing artificial intelligence to ease the process of selling a vehicle on their platform. The tedious work of copying information from the vehicle registration document into some web form can be automated with the help of smart text spotting systems. The seller takes a picture of the document and the necessary information is extracted&amp;nbsp;automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce the components of a text spotting system including the subtasks of object detection and character object recognition (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OCR&lt;/span&gt;). In view of our use case, we elaborate on the challenges of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OCR&lt;/span&gt; in documents with various distortions and artefacts which rule out off-the-shelve products for this&amp;nbsp;task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an introduction of semi-supervised learning based on generative adversarial networks (GANs), we evaluate the performance gains of this method compared to supervised learning. More specifically, for a varying amount of labelled data the accuracy of a convolution neural network (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CNN&lt;/span&gt;) is compared to a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GAN&lt;/span&gt; which uses additionally unlabelled data during the training&amp;nbsp;phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that GANs significantly outperform classical CNNs in use cases with a lack of labelled data. Regarding our use case of extracting information from vehicle registration documents, we show that our text spotting system easily exceeds an accuracy of 99.5% thus making it applicable in a real-world use&amp;nbsp;case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was presented at &lt;a href="https://conferences.oreilly.com/artificial-intelligence/ai-eu-2018/public/schedule/detail/70158"&gt;O&amp;#8217;Reilly &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; Conference 2018&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://de.pycon.org/schedule/talks/performance-evaluation-of-gans-in-a-semi-supervised-ocr-use-case/"&gt;PyCon.de 2018 Karlsruhe&lt;/a&gt;. The slides are available on &lt;a href="https://de.slideshare.net/FlorianWilhelm2/performance-evaluation-of-gans-in-a-semisupervised-ocr-use-case"&gt;SlideShare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="800" height="500"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/XniwzOCWi2c'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="machine-learning"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="GANs"></category><category term="semi-supervised"></category></entry><entry><title>Bridging the Gap: from Data Science to Production</title><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/2018/07/bridging_the_gap_from_ds_to_prod/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-25T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-25T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Florian Wilhelm</name></author><id>tag:florianwilhelm.info,2018-07-25:/2018/07/bridging_the_gap_from_ds_to_prod/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A recent but quite common observation in industry is that although there is an overall high adoption of data science, many companies struggle to get it into production. Huge teams of well-payed data scientists often present one fancy model after the other to their managers but their proof of concepts …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A recent but quite common observation in industry is that although there is an overall high adoption of data science, many companies struggle to get it into production. Huge teams of well-payed data scientists often present one fancy model after the other to their managers but their proof of concepts never manifest into something business relevant. The frustration grows on both sides, managers and data&amp;nbsp;scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my talk I elaborate on the many reasons why data science to production is such a hard nut to crack. I start with a taxonomy of data use cases in order to easier assess technical requirements. Based thereon, my focus lies on overcoming the two-language-problem which is Python/R loved by data scientists vs. the enterprise-established Java/Scala. From my project experiences I present three different solutions, namely 1) migrating to a single language, 2) reimplementation and 3) usage of a framework. The advantages and disadvantages of each approach is presented and general advices based on the introduced taxonomy is&amp;nbsp;given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, my talk also addresses organisational as well as problems in quality assurance and deployment. Best practices and further references are presented on a high-level in order to cover all facets of data science to&amp;nbsp;production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my talk I hope to convey the message that breakdowns on the road from data science to production are rather the rule than the exception, so you are not alone. At the end of my talk, you will have a better understanding of why your team and you are struggling and what to do about&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was presented at &lt;a href="https://ep2018.europython.eu/conference/talks/bridging-the-gap-from-data-science-to-production"&gt;EuroPython 2018&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.codetalks.de/de/2018/programm/#talk-255"&gt;Code.Talks 2018&lt;/a&gt;. The slides are available on &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/FlorianWilhelm2/bridging-the-gap-from-data-science-to-production"&gt;SlideShare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="800" height="500"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/ItcMqTR7Cds'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="production"></category></entry><entry><title>How mobile.de brings Data Science to Production for a Personalized Web Experience</title><link href="https://florianwilhelm.info/2018/07/how_mobilede_brings_ds_to_prod_for_a_personalized_web_experience/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-07T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-07T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Florian Wilhelm</name></author><id>tag:florianwilhelm.info,2018-07-07:/2018/07/how_mobilede_brings_ds_to_prod_for_a_personalized_web_experience/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As Germany&amp;#8217;s biggest online car marketplace, &lt;a href="https://www.mobile.de/"&gt;mobile.de&lt;/a&gt; provides a personalized web experience. Our Data Team leverages the interactions of our users to infer their preferences. For this tasks we often apply Python and Spark to wrangle massive amounts of data. In this talk, we are going to present …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As Germany&amp;#8217;s biggest online car marketplace, &lt;a href="https://www.mobile.de/"&gt;mobile.de&lt;/a&gt; provides a personalized web experience. Our Data Team leverages the interactions of our users to infer their preferences. For this tasks we often apply Python and Spark to wrangle massive amounts of data. In this talk, we are going to present our personalization use-cases as well as the application of PySpark in&amp;nbsp;production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a short introduction we will present various data use cases that where tackled by &lt;a href="https://www.mobile.de/"&gt;mobile.de&lt;/a&gt;, Germany&amp;#8217;s largest vehicle marketplace online, in the last two years. In a combined endeavour &lt;a href="https://www.inovex.de/en/"&gt;inovex&lt;/a&gt;, an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; project house with a strong focus on digitalization, has supported &lt;a href="https://www.mobile.de/"&gt;mobile.de&lt;/a&gt; on this&amp;nbsp;voyage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personalized web experience is a commonly used term in e-commerce that is hard to grasp. Thus, we illustrate how mobile.de understands personalized web experience and outline its features as well as opportunities. In more detail, we will elaborate on the Bayesian framework that we use to approximate user preferences. Furthermore, we discuss the modelling of user intent and how this can be used to understand the buyer&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the data science and modelling aspects of the use cases we will also dive into the technical details and how we solved them with the help of Python and Spark (PySpark). In more detail we will address the implementation of efficient User-Defined-(Aggregation)-Functions with Pandas in PySpark as well as the management of isolated environments and dependencies with&amp;nbsp;PySpark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will conclude our talk with the benefits of a personalized web experience for the users of &lt;a href="https://www.mobile.de/"&gt;mobile.de&lt;/a&gt; which was achieved with the help of Python and PySpark in&amp;nbsp;production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was presented at &lt;a href="https://pydata.org/berlin2018/schedule/presentation/59/"&gt;PyData 2018 Berlin&lt;/a&gt; together with my colleague Markus Schüler from &lt;a href="https://www.mobile.de/"&gt;mobile.de&lt;/a&gt; and the slides are available on &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/FlorianWilhelm2/how-mobilede-brings-data-science-to-production-for-a-personalized-web-experience"&gt;SlideShare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="800" height="500"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/fFiI6HABW-0'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="production"></category><category term="spark"></category><category term="big data"></category></entry></feed>